Guide to the Gaber/Kline Family Papers, 1916-2017 MS 854
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Gaber / Kline Family Papers
1916-2017
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Gaber, Sara Jo
MS 854
4 Linear Feet 4 boxes; map drawer 189
This collection is made up of four boxes containing certificates, correspondence, event materials, memorabilia, news clippings, photographs, scrapbooks, and publications from the Gaber/Kline Family, spanning from 1916 to 2017.
Scope and Contents
Certificates, correspondence, event materials, memorabilia, news clippings, photographs, scrapbooks, and publications document the lives of members of the Gaber and Kline families and their involvement in the Houston Jewish Community from 1916-2017. Of particular interest are the Gaber Family Haggadah produced in 2017 containing an extensive Gaber/Kline family tree, as well as the "This is Your Life Leo Gaber" scrapbook compiled by Morelle Gaber in 1954.
Biographical / Historical
Jacob Gaber and Ernestina Grunberg Gaber were born in Romania and married in Bucharest in 1896. In 1900, the two immigrated to Houston where they founded the J. Gaber Company, a dry goods and plumbing supplies company. They had four children, Hermina, Fred, Sophie, and Leo. Jacob died on November 3, 1927, and Ernestina died on January 2, 1963. Both are buried at Beth Yeshurun Cemetery.
Hermina was born November 22, 1897 in Romania. She married Morris Rosen on December 14, 1919, and died on August 26, 1981. She is also buried at Beth Yeshurun Cemetery. Sophie was born on June 4, 1903, in Houston, Texas. She married Leo Block in 1922, and died on April 2, 1994, in Houston. Leo Gaber was born on June 11, 1904. He followed in his father's footsteps and ran the family business. Leo Gaber married Morelle Solman on June 14, 1927.
Morelle's father Phillip Solman was born in Riga, Latvia on July 15, 1867 and immigrated to the United States in 1887. Morelle's mother, Hattie Perlstein, born 1872, immigrated to the United States in 1889. Phillip Solman and Hattie Perlstein married on August 23, 1891, in Houston, Texas. The Solmans were grocers and had four children: Libbie, Winnie, Jerome Benjamin, and Morelle. Libbie Solman was born October 10, 1892, and married Ben Scheps. She died October 31, 1963, and is buried at Beth Israel. Jerome Benjamin Solman was born on February 15, 1902, and died January 3, 1968. Morelle Solman was born on April 28, 1908.
Morelle and Leo Gaber had one son, Jacob Arnold (J.A.) Gaber, born on March 30, 1930. J.A. also followed his father into the family business and the Gaber Company later became primarily a plumbing supply company. Morelle died on November 22, 1986. Leo died on September 23, 1990. Both are buried at Beth Yeshurun Cemetery.
J.A. Gaber married Sara Jo (Dodie) Kline on May 14, 1952, in Houston, Texas. Dodie Kline was born in Houston on July 29, 1934, to Harry J. Kline from Tyler, Texas, and Adrienne Fibush Kline from Oakland, California. J.A. and Dodie Gaber had four children: Bradley Edward, Gwynne, Kerry Wayne, and Ellen Ann. Bradley Edward was born August 17, 1954. He married Ellen Brodsky in 1978, and died on June 30, 2012. Gwynne Gaber was born June 2, 1956, and married Alan Ross in 1979. Kerry Wayne, was born September 12, 1958, and married Mary Perrinod in 1981. Ellen Ann was born August 3, 1962, and married Marc Sands.
J.A. Gaber died on February 18, 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research without restriction. Stored on-site at the Woodson Research Center.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged in eight series as follows: Series I: Certificates; Series II: Correspondence; Series III: Event Materials; Series IV: Memorabilia; Series V: News Clippings/Newsletters Series VI: Photographs Series VII: Publications; Series VIII: Oversize
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sara Jo (Dodie) Gaber donated the Gaber/Kline Family Papers in April of 2019.
Separated Materials
1947 El Oroso was removed from the collection and cataloged, onsite at the Woodson Research Center. Call number: LD7501 .S26 .O76 1947
Index Terms
Subjects
Jews and Jewish life
Document Types
certificates; letters (correspondence); memorabilia; newspapers; photographs; publications; scrapbooks
Subjects (Persons)
Gaber, Sara Jo
- Series I: Certificates, 1968-1974
  - Hadassah Service Award to Hetty Solman, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congregation Beth Israel, Memorial Resolution for Arline Fibush, 1968-03 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate of Appreciation to Morelle Gaber for Grand Juror Service, 1974-08-01 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1960-1974
  - Mother's Day Telegram to Morelle Gaber, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Telegrams Congratulating J.A. Gaber on Graduation, 1935-05-30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence to Leo Gaber, 1960-04-28-1966-05-11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence to Leo and Sophie Block, 1967; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to Morelle Gaber, 1974-08-27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III: Event Materials, 1947-1950
  - San Jacinto High School Commencement Program, 1947-05-29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sarah Jo (Dodie) Kline Confirmation, Congregation Beth Israel, Photograph, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Congregation Beth Israel Confirmation Service (Program, Photograph), 1949-06-03 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - National Council of Jewish Women "Inside Houston" Event Program, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series IV: Memorabilia, n.d.
  - Leather Postcard, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Harry Zapp Campaign Card, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series V: Newspaper/Newsletters, 1956-1968
  - News Clippings, 1956-1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Photographs, 1917-1974
  - Portrait of Ernestina Gaber, Houston, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sophie and Leo Block Photographs, 1914 - circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Congregation Adath Yeshurun, Confirmation Class of 1917 Photograph (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - J. Gaber Co. Business Card with Photograph of Sophie Block, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, circa 1920-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Wedding Portrait of Morelle Gaber, c. 1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gaber Family Photographs, circa 1928-1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Houston Jewish Youth Organization Group Photos, circa 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gaber Event Photos, including Family Portraits, 1955; 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Leo and Morelle Gaber Photographs (Grand Jury), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Harris County Grand Jury, 176th District Court Group Photo, 1974-05 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Disassembled Photo Album, Including Photocopies, circa 1920-2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series VII: Publications, 1946-2017
  - San Jacinto High School Directory, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gates of Prayer for Young People, Illustrated by Brad Gaber, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Brad Gaber Illustrations, Congregation Beth Israel, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gaber Family Haggadah, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series VIII: Oversize, 1929-1968
  - Jewish National Fund Freedom Forest Certificate (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sophie Gaber Block "The Girl Graduate" Senior Memory Book, 1916-1920 (Box 3)
  - Yahrzeit Certificate in Memory of Hattie Solman's Death, 1929-05-26 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gaber Family Portrait, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Harris County Grand Jury Group Photo, 1965; 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "This is Your Life Leo Gaber" Scrapbook, 1954-06-11 (Box 4)
  - Chart of Family Tree, n.d. (Map-drawer 189, Folder 10)